Boker tov, welcome to the penultimate day of מסכת נדה Maseches Niddah
and of all of the ש"ס. Shas. We pick up, today's דף
Daf is ע"ב, Ayin Beis, 72. We pick up at the very
bottom of ע"א עמוד א' Ayin Alef Amud Alef at the משנה,
Mishnah, last משנה Mishnah of
the ע"א, Ayin Alef, excuse me, last משנה Mishnah of the מסכת.
Maseches. Let's take a look. הרואה יום אחד עשר, Ha-ro'ah yom achad
asar, she sees blood on the 11th day. Last משנה Mishnah of
all of the גמרא. Gemara. Well, right, if you, of גמרא, Gemara,
right. There's others in other משניות. Mishnayos. Okay. הרואה יום אחד עשר.
Ha-ro'ah yom achad asar. Now, of course, we've been talking a little
bit of a digression, although it's hard to know with the organization
here what's exactly a digression, what's not. But anyway, something that was
not really directly relevant for primary הלכות נדה, Hilchos Niddah, and in
this last משנה Mishnah we go back to a final aspect of
direct הלכות נדה, Hilchos Niddah, not necessarily as is applicable today, but
still in terms of the basic structure. And it says the following:
A woman who sees on the 11th day. 11th day meaning the
11 days after her period has been over, or after the seven
days. A woman gets her period, from days 1 through 7 she's
a נדה Niddah biblically. We're at the biblical level here. Then for
the next 11 days, days 8 through 18, she if she bleeds
three days in a row, she's a
זבה גדולה Zavah Gedolah with seven clean days. If she bleeds one
or two days, she's a זבה קטנה Zavah Ketanah and she needs
one clean day. Now, all that is very nice if she bleeds
on up through day 10. If she bleeds up through day 10
one day, then she needs one clean day, day 11. But let's
say, asks the משנה, Mishnah, she bleeds for the first time on
day 11 of that days 8 through 18, the very last of
the 11 days in which she can become a זבה. Zavah. That
day 11 is
if you demand a clean day, the clean day is going to
be in the נדה Niddah period. Right? And even if she bleeds
the next day, it won't make her, day 18, right? Let's say
11 of the זבה Zavah period, day 18 from the onset of
menstruation. Right? I'm using sort of two numbering systems here. But for
now, let's just to be clear call it day 11. But it
means from when the זבה Zavah period began. So she bleeds day
11. Even if she bleeds the next day, it doesn't make her
a זבה. Zavah. If she bleeds the next day, she's what? What
is she? A נדה. Niddah. Right? She's now after the 11-day period.
If she bleeds the next day, so what purpose would it have
in making her wait to go to the מקוה Mikvah until she
had a period of not bleeding on the next day, since the
next day doesn't connect to her זבה Zavah status anyway? So that
is the debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai. Does when she bleeds on day 11 only, does she need
to wait until the morning of day 12, which is the נדה
Niddah period, before going to the מקוה? Mikvah? So let's take a
look.
What's the other option?
Well, let's take a look. הרואה יום אחד עשר, Ha-ro'ah yom achad
asar, she sees on day 11, וטבלה לערב, ve-tavlah la-erev, she doesn't
wait until the morning of day 12. She goes to the מקוה
Mikvah that night. She didn't do any waiting. Okay, I mean, that
day ran out, but she didn't wait a part of the next
day. She just went straight to the מקוה. Mikvah. ושימשה, ve-shimshah, and
then she has sex. בית שמאי אומר, Beis Shammai omer, so בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says she is completely biblically still a זבה. Zavah.
Even on day 11, you need a part of day 12. מטמאין
משכב ומושב, metam'in mishkav u-moshav,
she and her husband would make seats that they sit on טמא.
tamei. Right? טומאת משכב ומושב tum'as mishkav u-moshav means she has the
full status of a נדה, Niddah, even though she's gone to the
מקוה, Mikvah, because it didn't count, because she needed part of day
12. וחייבין בקרבן, ve-chayavin be-korban, and they both have to bring a
קרבן korban for having had sex when she was still, she was
a זבה. Zavah. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says even on day
11, you need a part of day 12 even though it's in
the נדה Niddah period. ובית הלל אומרים, ve-Beis Hillel omrim, top of
ע"ב עמוד א', Ayin Beis Amud Alef, בית הלל Beis Hillel says
פטורין מן הקרבן. pturin min ha-korban. No,
she's not a זבה. Zavah. Biblically, she can go to the מקוה
Mikvah that night. She doesn't need to wait the next morning because
you're already in the נדה Niddah period. However, what he doesn't say
is he doesn't say that they're טהור tahor because דרבנן derabbanan implicitly,
and this will be spelled out very clearly in a ברייתא Braisa
in the גמרא, Gemara, she, you know, he's concerned that you don't
mix up day 11 with day 10, or day 9, or whatever.
So he wants to דרבנן derabbanan sort of, you know, apply חומרות.
chumros. He doesn't want to make you think you can bleed and
go to the מקוה Mikvah that night as a general rule. But
nevertheless, he says biblically you're really totally טהור, tahor, there's no קרבן.
korban. דרבנן, Derabbanan, you have to wait until the next morning before
you can go to the מקוה Mikvah and so therefore דרבנן derabbanan
you're still טמא. tamei. Okay, so that's if you didn't wait at
all. Now, טבלה ביום שלאחריו. tavlah be-yom she-le-acharav. Now, she did something
which everybody should agree works. She waits until the morning of day
12 and then goes to the מקוה. Mikvah. A normal זבה קטנה,
Zavah Ketanah, a woman who bled one day during the 11-day period,
that's if she bleeds on day 6. She goes to the מקוה
Mikvah the morning of day 7. You don't need the full next
day, you only need a partial. Okay, however, you will remember that
if she goes to the morning, let's say morning of day 7
if she bled on day 6, so on the one hand she's
טהור, tahor, but on the other hand if she bleeds later that
day, then retroactively it undermines having gone to the מקוה Mikvah that
morning. Right? So let's take a look at what will happen here
when it's day 11 and day 12. טבלה ביום שלאחריו, tavlah be-yom
she-le-acharav, she waited until the beginning of day 12 and then went
to the מקוה. Mikvah. ושימשה ביתה, ve-shimshah beisah, and then she had
sex Beisah.
The husband is called ביתה? beisah?
No, I don't think so. I think oh I think oh I
think. I thought, well that's interesting. I assumed the woman is normally
called בית, bayit, the woman is normally the one, you know, דבסאי
הוא ביתא. devasai hu beita. She used her בית. bayit. She used
her בית. bayit. I understand that it means that the בית bayit
is her interior, meaning with the same way the woman's body is
compared to a בית bayit and her genitalia and her sort of
reproductive organs are called, you know, the חדר, cheder, the עליה, aliya,
the פרוזדור. prosdor. They just said ושמשא.
veshimsha. Yes, but why ביתה? beita?
Well,
I don't know,
I don't know. I think it's a good question. You're right. When
the Gemara normally speaks about, the Gemara does say תשמיש. tashmish. It
says, sometimes the Gemara says תשמיש המטה tashmish hamita using the bed.
Sometimes, you're right, it just says תשמיש. tashmish. So it's an interesting
question whether it says, I would have to check whether in the
Gemara, yeah, the Gemara just says ושמשא. veshimsha. Yeah, and here at
the beginning it says ומשמשא, umeshamsha, so yes. But it's also by
the man, sometimes it says תשמיש המטה. tashmish hamita. But anyway, I
understand that for the woman, I mean I don't know if it's
better or worse, but I think that בית, bayit, we never use
בית bayit to refer to the man.
I think בית bayit means that her בית, bayit, you know, her
interior. So she allowed her husband to have sex with her to
enter into her house.
It basically means that she used her interior.
Right, she allowed her husband to enter into her house. That's more
or less what I think it's getting at.
But it's ושמשא, veshimsha, she's the active. Her ושמשא. veshimsha. So you're
saying passive.
I know, but alright.
Anyway, if she actively opens her doors.
No, I'm saying, I'm saying she used her house. I'm saying she
used her house, that's what it says.
How about calling her husband her בית, bayit, just like
she's always called his
בית? bayit? Maybe.
Right. Possibly, but I don't think so. But possibly. I want to
remind you by the way that the Gemara's used for, you know,
the male genitalia is שמש, shamash, and when it talks about for
example,
you know, do בדיקה bedika right after sex, it says it's like,
you know, somebody is standing, the שמש shamash is standing on the
opening of the door. So it very much uses he is the
תשמיש, tashmish, he is the שמש, shamash, she is the house he
is entering into her and so on. So that was my understanding
of this. But okay, it's open. Let's see what the Gemara says
next. I don't think so, but you want to say fine. Anyway,
the Gemara says like this: okay, so she had sex, ואחר כך
ראתה, ve-achar kach ra-ata, and then she bled. Now again, here, as
opposed to she bled she saw on day five and then went
to the mikvah on day six and bled, where then it would
be a continuation of her zavah status and it would uproot her
having gone to the mikvah. Here, if she bleeds on day 12,
she becomes a נדה. niddah. It does not continue her זבה zavah
status and it's a new status of her being a נדה. niddah.
So therefore, what does that do to the period between having gone
to the mikvah and bleeding, since the bleeding is now a new
status, not a continuation of the old? So it says, בית שמאי
אומרים מטמא משכב ומושב ופטור מן הקרבן. Beit Shammai omrim metamei mishkav
u-moshav u-patur min hakorban. In that case, I would admit that it's
only rabbinic. Meaning again, what happened? She went to the mikvah on
day 12, had sex, and then bled. Her bleeding makes her a
נדה. niddah. It does not make her a זבה. zavah. It does
not continue the status of day 11. So actually, what happened between
going to the mikvah on day 12 and bleeding is all going
to remain טהור. tahor. It's not going to be uprooted biblically. Okay,
so even there, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says between going to the
mikvah and bleeding, if you had sex then and then it turned
out that you bled later that day, the bleeding later, the new
status of a נדה, niddah, during that thing you were טהור, tahor,
you're not obligated in a קרבן. korban. Rabbinically, I'm going to consider
you טמא tamei because it's easy to confuse that scenario with the
same thing happening during the 11 days, but biblically you're okay, you
don't bring a קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's what בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says. In that case, he agrees to that idea that it's
rabbinically טמא tamei but biblically no קרבן. korban. ובית הלל אומרים, u-Veit
Hillel omrim, Beit Hillel says הרי זו גרגרן, harei zu gargeran, גרגרת.
gargerat.
In that case, you're too like over, basically you're too quick to
sin, which basically means like it's a derogatory comment,
like we don't look favorably on that. It's not even a question
about how much it makes it forbidden, because according to this, you
actually gone to the mikvah before having had sex. So it's true,
had that happened when you were a זבה zavah and then retroactively,
you know, during the 11 days, retroactively it would have undermined what
it would have done, but here actually you waited the next day
and you went to the mikvah. So בית הלל Beit Hillel says
you're like asking for trouble. But it's not clear whether it's even
rabbinically, well, because you'll come to mix that case up with a
similar case during the זבה zavah period. It's true now you're not
asking for trouble, but it's a little being a little bit too
careless. What's the careless part? When you go to the mikvah on,
you went to the mikvah on day 12, saw on day 11,
went to the mikvah morning of day 12 and then had sex
before day 12 was out. So in that case, although really it's
true that if you bleed later, it does not undermine your status
now because now it's a new thing, it's נדה Niddah not זבה,
Zavah, so actually for this day you're really being completely care, you
know, you're not being careful. There's nothing wrong that can happen, but
you're being sloppy might be better word than careless because that type
of a practice will lead to doing similar things during the 11-day
period. And then, if you go to the מקוה, Mikvah, let's say
on day 6 after having bled on day 5, have sex and
bleed later on day 6, retroactively the whole thing will be ruined.
Not wait, if you go
to the, if you bleed on day 5 and go to the
מקוה Mikvah morning of day 6, technically you're טהורה Tehorah now and
you could have sex and you could touch תרומה Terumah and so
on, but it's risky and it's not it's not careful because if
you bleed later that day, retroactively it'll undermine having gone to the
מקוה Mikvah and everything will have been problematic. So if you did
it sometimes on 5 and 6, you are not supposed to do
anything later that day until even if you've gone to the מקוה
Mikvah until the day is complete, until the night of 7, right,
until that nightfall. Okay.
So similarly, if you had a similar scenario on 11 and 12,
right, then in that case technically even if you bled later on
12, you're totally safe. Okay. But בית הלל Beis Hillel says it's
like it's still, you know, improper because if you do it on
11 and 12, you come to do it on 5 and 6.
And if you do it on 5 and 6 and you bleed
later that day, it's two degrees removed. It's true. 11 and 12
could lead to 5 and 6 and if you do it on
5 and 6, it could lead to a case of bleeding later
that day and it being a problem. Which is why his language
is not so strong. It's stuff like that's improper, that's asking for
trouble. However, there is a גמרא Gemara earlier on that said that
means you shouldn't do it, that it's אסור, Asur, but it's not
so clear from the משנה. Mishnah. Okay. So, yes, I want one
more point I do want to say about this, which we have
a fascinating הלכה Halacha according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. According to
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, this woman biblically can't go to the מקוה
Mikvah till the day of day 12. She needs a little bit
of day 12. But even if she bleeds on day 12, it
doesn't affect her status as a זבה. Zavah. Right? If she bleeds
on day 12, it's a totally new status as a נדה. Niddah.
Right? That everybody agrees
to after the, well, even before the מקוה, Mikvah, it would not
connect her זבה Zavah status. It would not, like, connect to her
זבה. Zavah. So ironically, right, what would be
the purpose of going to the מקוה Mikvah if she's bleeding?
Well, okay, yes, obviously she couldn't go to the מקוה, Mikvah, but
the point is any bleeding on day 12 is a new status
of a נדה. Niddah. And if she's gone to the מקוה Mikvah
and bleeds later on day 12, it does not continue her זבה
Zavah status. And even having said all of that, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai still says she can't go to the מקוה Mikvah until a
little bit of day 12 begins and that she hasn't bled a
little bit of day 12 yet, okay? Question.
So after 18 days,
any bleeding makes her נדה Niddah again?
Right. But when wouldn't she usually expect that her period's going to
begin later
than, yes, but the point, the implicit point seeming to be that
a cycle could be as short as 19 days. Anything shorter than
that, anything from day 8 to 18, is considered to not be
part of the menstrual cycle and therefore makes it זבה Zavah bleeding.
Okay. So that's if she's gone to the מקוה.
Mikvah. If she, let's say, saw blood during day 12, would she
go to the מקוה Mikvah that night?
If she saw blood during day 12? No, then she becomes a
נדה. Niddah.
So she wouldn't do anything to enter a זבה Zavah status?
You mean according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, let's say she was
bleeding on day 12 itself and couldn't go to the מקוה Mikvah
on day 12, would she need somewhere on day 17,
a clean day, to count all the way back for her day,
for her day 11 that she had a while ago?
Or would night of 12 now just end the זבה? Zavah?
No, no, that she can't do. No, no, because day 12 needs
to count as a clean day according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
That she can't do. But the question is, can you have a
clean day much later according to בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? Interesting. Not
sure, have to think about it. Okay. Now, ומודים, U'modim, they agree,
ברואה בתוך י"א יום, B'roah b'toch yud-aleph yom, the standard case, she
saw during the 11 days, let's say the example we're giving on
day 5, וטבלה לערב, V'tavlah l'erev, and went to the מקוה Mikvah
the night of 5, that case, that's biblically not good. She needs
a little bit of the next day. ושמשה, V'shimshah, and then she
has sex, sex, שמטמאים משכב ומושב, She'metamim mishkav u'moshav, even if she
didn't bleed at all, she's not
טהורה, Tehorah, she didn't wait a little bit of day 6. שמטמאים
משכב ומושב, She'metamim mishkav u'moshav, that things she sits on, they sit
on are טמאים, Teme'im, וחייבים בקרבן, V'chayavim b'korban,
and they're both obligated to bring a קרבן, Korban, because that case
didn't work at all. Everybody agrees in the middle of the 11
days, you need a bit of the next day. And they also
agree, טבלה ביום שלאחריו, Tavlah b'yom she'leacharyo, if she went to the
מקוה Mikvah on the beginning of day 6, ושמשה, V'shimshah, and had
sex, in that case, right now you are טהורה, Tehorah, it's true.
But you're really risking it because a bleeding later will uproot having
gone to the מקוה. Mikvah. So in that case, they agree, הרי
זה תרבות רעה, Harei zeh tarbus ra'ah, as opposed to just גרגרן,
Gargeran, which is like asking for trouble. תרבות רעה Tarbus ra'ah is
like, you know, bad behavior. ומגען ובעילתן תלויים, U'maga'an u'be'ilasan tluyim,
anything you touch and any sex that you have, the status is,
is תלויים, Tluyim, is, is dependent. But there's a better word than
dependent. Anyway, is to be determined because it's going to depend on
whether you bleed later that day or not. So the status is...
anything you touch and any sex that you have based on whether
you bleed later that day. Meaning, so therefore, if you were to
have sex today, you're basically doing a potential איסור כרת. Issur Kares.
If you were to touch תרומה Terumah today, you are potentially violating
תרומה. Terumah. It all is going to be determined whether you bleed
later this day. So that is certainly definitely forbidden. Technically you're טהור
Tahor but it's forbidden, at least rabbinically if not worse, to engage
in any problematic behavior because your status might change. Yes.
It doesn't really seem fair to make something retroactively wrong based on
the future.
Yeah, but the alternative is, remember the idea that you can go
to the מקווה Mikveh at the beginning of the day, it starts
from an idea that you need a full clean day. But we
let you go to the מקווה Mikveh based on the beginning of
the day just on the principle of מקצת היום ככולו, Miktzat Hayom
Kekulo, that a part of the day counts as the whole day.
But in principle we're like saying to you, you don't have to
wait, in principle you should be waiting till night. You need a
whole clean day. But we're going to make it easy for you
know, we're going to count the beginning of the day as if
you waited the whole day. But because it's count as if, if
later the day proves otherwise that it hasn't been a clean day,
so you know, you can't count the beginning as if the whole
as if it's to represent the whole day as being clean. So
the way to think about it is is that like you know,
really you should wait the whole day. This allows you to go
to the מקווה Mikveh earlier based on this principle of מקצת היום
ככולו. Miktzat Hayom Kekulo.
But you're saying it would encourage it. Well, that's why there was
an opinion earlier in the גמרא Gemara that you're not that you
even that you shouldn't be going to the מקווה Mikveh during the
day because it's just asking for trouble. Not only should you not
act on having gone to the מקווה, Mikveh, you shouldn't even go
to the מקווה Mikveh because of that concern.
Okay. Alright, so let's take a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: ושוין בטובלת לילה לזבה שאינה טבילה.
Veshoavin betovelet lailah lezavah she'einah tevilah. So you see, I was going
to mention the משנה, Mishnah, it's interesting always, you know, how the
משניות Mishnayot are constructed. But besides that there's been a lot of
questions about general organization. But the משנה Mishnah in general assumes you're
already in the conversation and you know the basic facts and starts
on a more usually starts on a more obscure point rather than
sort of building up the first principles. So here the משנה Mishnah
started on a debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel uBeit
Shammai day eleven, and it didn't tell you the basic principles of
what happens in day five and six, right? I told you that.
The משנה Mishnah only said it at the end. The ברייתא Braita
reverses the order, makes life a little easier for you. So here's
what the ברייתא Braita says: ושוין בטובלת לילה לזבה, Veshoavin betovelet lailah
lezavah, a normal זבה Zavah that goes to the מקווה Mikveh at
night let's say after bleeding on day five, she goes at night.
שאינה טבילה, She'einah tevilah, it doesn't count at all, you need a
little bit of day six. ושוין ברואה בתוך אחד עשר יום וטבלה
לערב ושמשה. Veshoavin beroah betoch achad asar yom vetavlah la'erev veshamshah. So
this is really repeating what it just said. That they agree that
if a woman who bled during the eleven days like on day
five and went in the at the night without waiting the next
day ושמשה veshamshah and had sex, שמטמא משכב ומושב וחייבת בקרבן. shemetama
mishkav umoshav vechayevet bekorban. And the fact that it doesn't work means
that if you went to the מקווה Mikveh at night without waiting
the next day that biblically still a נידה, Niddah, the טבילה Tevilah
didn't work, the things you sit on and husband sits and the
woman and the husband and the man sits on are טמא, Tamei,
and they're both חייב בקרבן Chayav bekorban if they've had sex. לא
נחלקו, Lo nechelku, that's in the middle of the eleven days. לא
נחלקו אלא ביום אחד עשר, Lo nechelku ela beyom achad asar, day
eleven itself. Where the next day is יום נדה Yom Niddah day.
שבית שמאי אומרים מטמא משכב ומושב וחייבת בקרבן. sheBeit Shammai omrim metama
mishkav umoshav vechayevet bekorban. And בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that's like
the middle days, you need a bit of day twelve to count.
Even though a new bleeding on day twelve won't retroactively change the
status, but at least you need a bit of day twelve. And
without that if you're there at night biblically טמא, Tamei, biblically חייב
בקרבן. Chayav bekorban. ובית הלל פוטרין מן הקרבן. uBeit Hillel potrin min
hakorban. בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's not a biblical issue, you
really are exempt from a קרבן, Korban, rabbinically I'll say you're טמא
Tamei because it's going to get confused with during the eleven days,
but biblically having gone the night of eleven you're fine and you
don't bring a קרבן. Korban. אמרו להן בית שמאי לבית הלל, Amru
lahen Beit Shammai leBeit Hillel, now we get this fleshed out a
little bit. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says to בית הלל: Beit Hillel:
מה שני יום אחד עשר מתוך אחד
עשר יום? Mah shani yom achad asar mitoch achad asar yom? Why
is day eleven different than the middle days? אם שוו לו לטומאה,
im shavu lo letumah, if you'll agree that if you go to
the מקווה Mikveh at the night of day eleven she's still טמאה,
Tmeiah, right parenthetically rabbinically, but בית שמאי Beit Shammai isn't sort of
making that point. They're saying look, you already admit that even if
she goes night of day eleven, you're going to say that outside
of קרבן, Korban, outside of sex, you know, she's still טמאה Tmeiah
for things she touches. So if you agree she's טמאה Tmeiah if
she doesn't wait a little bit of day twelve, לא ישוו לו
לקרבן? lo yishvu lo lekorban? So you should say the same, you
should say that she's biblically טמאה Tmeiah and she should have to
bring a קרבן. Korban. אמרו להן בית הלל לבית שמאי, Amru lahen
Beit Hillel leBeit Shammai, so בית הלל Beit Hillel said back to
בית שמאי: Beit Shammai: לא, Lo, no. אם אמרתם בתוך אחד עשר
יום, Im amartem betoch achad asar yom, when it's during the eleven
days, not the last
day, שכן יום שלאחר מצטרף עמו לזיבה. sheken yom shele'achar mitztaref imo
lezivah. The next day can combine with it. The next day is
still the זבה Zavah period. And not only that, if she had
three days in a row she'll be זבה גדולה. Zavah Gedolah. So
there I will say without a little bit of the next day
the טבילה Tevilah doesn't count. תאמרו ביום אחד עשר, Tomru beyom achad
asar, would you say about day
eleven? שאין יום שלאחר מצטרף עמו לזיבה. she'ein yom shele'achar mitztaref imo
lezivah. There's no following day that combines to her זבה Zavah status.
The next day is in your נידה Niddah period. So in that
case you biblically do not need a little bit of the next
day. אמרו להן בית שמאי, Amru lahen Beit Shammai, so בית שמאי
Beit Shammai still says fine, I get your point why eleven is
different, but I'm bothered about your lack of... consistency. היא שמידותיכם. Hi
she-midosaychem. So if you want to say that, be consistent. אם שבעה
לו לטומאה, Im shiva lo le-tumah, if you're going to say that
it's that that day 11 is like the middle days, that it's
טמא, tamay, which is what you say, you say if she goes
the night of 11, she's still טמא tamay for purposes other than
a קרבן. korban. So יש לו לקרבן. yeish lo le-korban. So if
you're going to say night of 11 doesn't work that she's טמא,
tamay, then say it doesn't work and she's obligated in a קרבן.
korban. אם לא שבעה לו לקרבן, Im lo shiva lo le-korban, and
if you're going to say that night of the 11 works and
she doesn't have to bring a קרבן, korban, she's not טמא, tamay,
לא יש לו לטומאה, lo yeish lo le-tumah, then don't say she's
טמא. tamay. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says to בית הלל, Beis
Hillel, look, I understand why you think day 11 is different, because
day 12 isn't part of the same period. But if day 11
is different, then say if she goes to the מקוה mikvah the
night of 11, she's totally טהורה. tehorah. How can you split your
vote? How can you say if she goes to the מקוה mikvah
the night of 11, she's טמא tamay for things she touches, but
if she had sex, she's not חייב chayav in a קרבן? korban?
How do you split your vote?
He's absolutely right.
Well, yes, except that he forgets the whole rabbinic move, not forgets,
but this is what בית הלל Beis Hillel is going to say
back, which is we can be strict about things when we want
to be. Okay, this whole, okay, so that's going to be... Is
it basically logic for rabbinic? No, so that's exactly the point. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai is arguing assuming that there's no rabbinic thing going
on here. It's all the basic principle, it's all biblical. So it
says biblically, if it works for קרבן, korban, it should work for
טומאה. tumah. And if it doesn't work for טומאה, tumah, it doesn't
work for קרבן. korban. Fine, that's true biblically. So let's see what
בית הלל's Beis Hillel's answer is. Whatever happened to rabbinic, you know,
גזירות? gezeirot? We certainly are, בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל
Beis Hillel were more than familiar with rabbinic laws. So let's take
a look. אמר להם בית הלל, Amar lahem Beis Hillel, so בית
הלל Beis Hillel says back to them, "No. אם הביאוני לידי טומאה
להחמיר," Im hevi'uni lidei tumah lehachmir,
notice by the way the subject of the verb here. If we
will bring her, or them actually, הביאוני, hevi'uni, anyway, if we will
bring him, anyway, to טומאה tumah to be strict, meaning if we
rabbinically are going to say that we're going to consider you טמא
tamay for strict, you know, to be strict on you, don't handle
תרומה terumah and so on, לא נביאנו לידי קרבן להקל, lo nevi'ennu
lidei korban lehakeil, we can't go ahead and be lenient and say
bring a קרבן. korban. Why is it being lenient to say bring
a קרבן? korban? Because if you're not obligated in קרבן korban and
you bring a קרבן, korban, we're letting you bring חולין chullin into
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, non-sanctified things into the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. So basically what he's saying is, look, biblically she's טהורה. tehorah.
Rabbinically I can make her טמאה, tmeia, but I can't make her
bring a קרבן korban rabbinically. So don't give me a problem that
I'm not being consistent. Basically she's טהורה, tehorah, but I'm giving a
rabbinic stringency because I don't want this to lead to leniency during
the basic
11 days.
Yeah, except בית הלל's Beis Hillel's going to point out that בית
שמאי Beis Shammai himself is aware of this split. So let's take
a look at the next line. ועוד מדבריכם אתם נושכים, Ve-od midivreichem
atem noshchim, you're bitten by your own words. Why? I like that
phrase. שאתם
אומרים, she-atem omrim, you say in the next scenario in the משנה,
Mishnah, שטבלה יום שלאחר ושמשה ואחר כך ראתה, she-tavlah yom shel achar
ve-shimshah ve-achar kach ra'asah, that if she actually waits a little bit
of day 12, goes to the מקוה mikvah and has sex, and
then she bleeds, right, that was the next case in the משנה,
Mishnah, that there we say biblically it doesn't uproot it retroactively, but
it's a rabbinic problem. So what do you say? You say in
that case, מטמאים משכב ומושב ופטורה מן הקרבן. metam'im mishkav u-moshav u-pturah
min ha-korban. You say just like I said when it was the
night of 11. You say if you wait day 12, go to
the מקוה, mikvah, have sex, touch תרומה terumah and then bleed, that
biblically it didn't uproot it. So, but so therefore you're not obligated
in the קרבן, korban, but the things you handled are טמא. tamay.
So you admit a similar type of a rabbinic status during that
period.
So there's two cases.
The first case is she didn't wait on day 12. She went
to the מקוה mikvah day 11, even if she bled...
she saw on day 11 and went on the night of 11.
And went on the night of 11, okay,
before the morning of 12. But all of this idea of waiting,
I'm sorry if I wasn't clear about that, all of this idea
of waiting into the next day means the morning of the next
day. Okay, yeah, I'm sorry if I wasn't clear. You need to
go into the morning.
So both count as going during the 24 hours of 12.
Yes. In the first case, yes. In the first case she bleeds
on day 11, she goes after צאת tzeis on night the night
leading into 12, and she doesn't bleed at all. But בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says that doesn't count. You need a little bit of
the morning of 12. Okay, so it doesn't count even if she
didn't bleed at all. And בית הלל Beis Hillel says biblically it
counts, rabbinically you're טמא. tamay. The next case is she waited into
the morning of 12, where everybody agrees that counts. And then she
bled later in the day, where everybody agrees it doesn't retroactively affect,
it doesn't connect. For that middle status, בית שמאי Beis Shammai says
there what בית הלל Beis Hillel said in the other case. No
קרבן, korban, biblically it's not a problem, but rabbinically you're טמא. tamay.
So בית הלל Beis Hillel says, look, you agree, you say the
same thing on the next day. Okay. So he says, אף אתם
היא שמידותיכם, Af atem hi she-midosaychem,
so say it back to yourself, be consistent. אם שבעה לו לטומאה
יש לו לקרבן, Im shiva lo le-tumah yeish lo le-korban, if you're
going to treat her טמאה tmeia in the case when she bleeds
later on day 12, then say she has to bring
a קרבן. korban. ואם לא שבעה לו לקרבן לא יש לו לטומאה,
ve-im lo shiva lo le-korban lo yeish lo le-tumah, don't say she's
טמאה. tmeia. So אלא, ella, what's the reason that you can give
her this, you know, split vote להחמיר lehachmir and not. You can
be strict rabbinically, but you're not going to be lenient in the
sense of have her bring a קרבן korban when she's not obligated.
הכי נמי, hachi nami, I say the same about the night if
you go to the מקוה mikvah the night following 11, להחמיר ולא
להקל. lehachmir velo lehakeil. You can be strict and not lenient, which
is a pretty good response. What was בית שמאי Beit Shammai thinking?
You know, so I don't really even know the answer, but you
know the whole discussion seems pretty funny that it's clear that the
answer is that we can have a rabbinic status.
Okay, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai thought maybe that even biblically you
need day 12.
That is his point, that is his point. But there's one thing
that in principle what they debate with בית הלל. Beit Hillel. I
say, I say you need day 12 biblically, you say you don't.
But then his next response to בית הלל Beit Hillel was, but
at least be consistent. And that was a... What do you mean
at least be consistent? Biblically I'm consistent, rabbinically I put a stringency
on it, you know? And you do the same thing. So that
issue of challenging me to say I'm not consistent is not a
good challenge. We can debate the principle, which is does day 11
require part of day 12 or not? But you can't... don't get
all in a tizzy that I split the vote and I'm not
consistent, because that's just a rabbinic stringency.
I would say he's just arguing the same but just this is
biblical.
I understand, but he didn't. He, after having argued the principle, then
he said why are you not consistent? Okay. So either say she's
totally טהור tahor or say she's totally טמאה. temeah. Alright, anyway so
that's their basic debate. Now let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes
from this. אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: משכבה ומושבה שבשני. mishkavah
u'moshavah she'bashini.
Now, since בית שמאי Beit Shammai is so strict, רב הונא Rav
Huna is going to say he's strict in another way that we
hadn't anticipated. משכבה ומושבה שבשני, mishkavah u'moshavah she'bashini, בית שמאי מטמאים אף
על פי שטבלה אף על פי שלא ראתה. Beit Shammai metame'im af
al pi she'tavla, af al pi she'lo ra'ata.
He says like this. He says, let's say a woman
in the middle of the 11 days, right, day
five. Bleeds on day five, goes to the מקוה mikvah day six.
He says given that בית שמאי Beit Shammai is so strict here
in various ways,
then we would say that if she goes to the מקוה, mikvah,
she went to the מקוה mikvah on day six and she handled
stuff, even if she didn't bleed for the rest of the day.
If she's going to bleed later on day six, biblically it'll undermine
it. But he says even if she doesn't bleed for the rest
of day six, we're going to consider her טמא tamei for the
rest of the day because she might bleed and it might undermine
it. So he's sort of saying given that we see בית שמאי
Beit Shammai is strict in various ways, although it's not exactly the
same, but given that he's strict that if she, you know, that
if she, right, that... well okay,
yes.
So let's take a look
at how the גמרא Gemara goes with this. I thought that was
more strict. They agreed totally, right? What? They agreed totally in the
middle of the 11 days.
Well, that's what the משנה Mishnah sounded like. He is saying no,
that actually בית שמאי Beit Shammai would be more strict in the
middle of the 11 days rabbinically, that even after having gone to
the מקוה, mikvah, you know, even not bleeding, her status is problematic.
So let's take a look. It definitely is a big חידוש chiddush
because the גמרא Gemara doesn't sound like it at all, and even
his analogy is going to be obviously easy to challenge. Let's see
the argument.
So he says like this: משכבה ומושבה שבשני, mishkavah u'moshavah she'bashini,
so her טומאה tumah status on the second day, meaning she bled
on the first day of the 11 let's say, and the second
day she went to the מקוה. mikvah. בית שמאי מטמאים אף על
פי שטבלה, Beit Shammai metame'im af al pi she'tavla, even though she
went to the מקוה, mikvah, and until now we're just saying that
her status is, you know, in abeyance, you know, in limbo, based
on whether she'll bleed later that day. He says no, rabbinically בית
שמאי Beit Shammai is going to treat her as טמאה temeah even
if she doesn't bleed. אף על פי שלא ראתה, af al pi
she'lo ra'ata, even if she didn't bleed. So that's a big חידוש,
chiddush, we never heard בית שמאי Beit Shammai say such a
thing. גמרא Gemara is
going to first think that
it's not a חידוש. chiddush. Let's take a look. אמר רב יוסף:
Amar Rav Yosef: מאי קא משמע לן? mai kamashma lan? תנינא, tenina,
we could figure it
out from the
משנה. Mishnah. How could we figure it out from the
משנה? Mishnah? What do we say in the משנה? Mishnah? טבל יום
כלכלה ושמשה בתה ואחר כך ראתה,
taval yom k'l'achla ve'shimsha betah
ve'achar kach ra'ata,
she waited into day 12, she had, you know, she went to
the מקוה, mikvah, she had sex, and then she bled. So that
case בית שמאי אומר מטמא משכב ומושב ופטור מן הקרבן. Beit Shammai
omer metamei mishkav u'moshav u'pattur min hakorban. That case retroactively she's טמאה.
temeah. So the גמרא Gemara assumes oh, it's a direct analogy. Since
day 12 you really don't, even if she bleeds it really won't
have any impact, and nevertheless בית שמאי Beit Shammai is going to
say when she bleeds later it retroactively undermines her status rabbinically because
why? Because we don't want her to confuse bleeding later on day
12 with bleeding later on a middle day, right? She went to
the מקוה mikvah on day 12, she bled later, בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is going to say I'm going to treat it like she
was טמאה temeah the whole time. Why? Because I don't want that
to confuse with a similar scenario happening on day 5 and 6
where if she bleeds later it will retroactively... so you see בית
שמאי Beit Shammai is concerned there it shouldn't get confused. So if
he's concerned with, you know. A little bit out with day 11
and 12 getting confused with 5 and 6, similarly, the assumption is
he should be concerned that if she goes to the מקווה mikvah
on day 6, you'll confuse bleeding later that not bleeding later that
day with bleeding later that day. Is that it's a very rough
analogy but do you see the point? בית שמאי Beis Shammai makes
גזירות. gezeiros. So his גזירה gezeira is if you wait 12 and
go to the מקווה mikvah and bleed later, even though technically that
middle period is okay, I'm assuming I'm going to treat it as
טמא tamei because 11 and 12 would get confused with 5 and
6. So similarly, if you bleed on day 5, wait day 6
and go to the מקווה, mikvah, even though now you're טהור tahor
if you don't bleed later that day, I'm going to treat you
as טמא tamei because I'm concerned that that scenario of not seeing
the rest of day 6 will get confused with seeing the rest
of day 6. Okay? You make one גזירה, gezeira, you make another.
סברא, Sevara, right? And then 11 and 12, even though she'd be
okay if she bled later.
Right,
but there's a difference. At day 6 she's yet to actually bleed.
So day 11 and 12 if she bleeds later it's nothing, but
at least there was the scenario where she did bleed later the
day. 5 and 6, the claim is that בית שמאי Beis Shammai
is going to say she's going to be treated as טמא tamei
even if she's gone to the מקווה, mikvah, even if she hasn't
bled. So to say you'll confuse a case of not bleeding with
a case of bleeding is different than saying you'll confuse 11 and
12 with bleeding with 5 and 6 with bleeding. One is just
a question of what time it happened. 11 and 12 is easy
to confuse with 5 and 6, right? Or with 10 and 11.
Right? It's just a question of what the day was. Okay, so
you can see you'll be strict on 11 and 12 to treat
it like 5 and 6 because it was a question of which
day. But it's the same scenario. You bled one day, went to
the מקווה mikvah the next morning, bled later the day. The only
question was it
11 and 12 or 5 and 6? This case it's a different
scenario. You're saying you're going to confuse 5 and 6 bleeding later
in 6 with not having bled the rest of 6. That's a
very obvious difference. Did I bleed later that day or not? So
that's what the retort is going to be. So let's take a
look. Okay. So you see it's pretty implicit that if they make
11 and 12 will mix up with 5 and 6, then one
case of 5 and 6 will mix up with another case of
5 and 6. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav
Kahana says, no, ראתה שונה. raasa shona. You've got to love it.
The whole everything I just said in three minutes he said in
two words. Okay, it's different when she sees, right? 11 and 12
she actually bled later that day. So okay, that is a problematic
case, you bleed later that day. We're going to be strict. Obviously
bleeding later the day is inherently problematic and it's easy to confuse
with the similar scenario of 11 and 12 with 5 and 6.
Here, 5 and 6 she went to the מקווה mikvah on 6
and nothing happened for the rest of the day. Who's to say
that בית שמאי Beis Shammai would be strict in that case?
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, ראתה מאי הוי? raasa mai havei?
But who cares if she bled on day 12? It's not הלכה
halachically meaningful for זבה, zavah, ראייה דנידה היא, reiyah de-Niddah hi, it's
still a נידה Niddah bleeding, so still הלכה halachically it's as if
she didn't bleed. So the point is it's very nice that הלכה
halachically it doesn't count, but experientially it's very significant. So אמר ליה
אביי לרב יוסף, amar leh Abaye le-Rav Yosef, אביי Abaye said back
to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, רב כהנא הכי קא קשיא ליה, Rav
Kahana hachi ka kashya leh, here's what רב כהנא Rav Kahana thought
the two cases were so different. בשלמא היכא דראתה, Bishlama heicha de-raasa,
I understand when it's 11 and 12 and she bleeds on 12,
you can say the bleeding on 12 is not part of זבה,
zavah, but nevertheless it's very easy to confuse, גזרינן ראייה דנידה אטו
ראייה דזבה, gazrinan reiyah de-Niddah atu reiyah de-zavah, that he can confuse
11 and 12 and bleeding on 12 with bleeding on 6. It's
really the same physical scenario, you know, circumstances. It's just a question
of which day. There you understand why to be strict with 11
and 12, because it could feel like a 5 and 6. היכא
דלא ראתה, heicha de-la raasa, but if 5 and 6 and she
didn't bleed for the rest of 6, מאי נגזור? mai nigzor? What
do you say, oh well, we have to treat you as if
you bled because you'll confuse a day of not bleeding with a
day of bleeding? I mean, once a woman is keeping all of
הלכות נידה, hilchos Niddah, she is not going to confuse a day
of not bleeding with a day of bleeding, okay, so why should
we make a גזירה? gezeira? So that doesn't...
exactly the same נידה Niddah and זבה zavah that a woman couldn't
differentiate...
well, the only difference is which day in the cycle you were.
But the experience would...
well, right, conceptually זבה zavah is הלכה halachically it doesn't matter what
the experiential, it's all the question of uterine blood.
Conceptually, the logic of זבה zavah is that it's not menstrual bleeding,
that bleeding between days 8 and 18 from your last period is
assumed to be non-menstrual.
But whether a woman could really tell the difference between day 18
and day 19 or day 16 and day 19... right, between her
really getting her period and mid-cycle bleeding, I assume she could tell,
but that's not based on the formal structure that the rabbis gave,
which is the question about which, you know, whether it is days
1 through 7 or 8 through 18 or 19 and onwards. That
was the whole difference, you know, within the formal structure being presented
here. Okay. So...
it sounds like בית שמאי Beis Shammai is not saying she confuses
a day of bleeding with not bleeding, it sounds like he's saying
I'm going to make a גזירה gezeira in case she does bleed
later.
No, that would be the הלכה halacha of... no, because he actually
He says that anything she touches the claim of רב הונא Rav
Huna was that if she goes to the מקוה mikvah on day
six, anything she touches even if she does not bleed for the
entire day six even if it is by the end of day
six she has not bled, anything she touched on day six is
treated as טמא. tamei. That was רב הונא’s Rav Huna claim. So
it is not just don't do things. It is not just be
careful don't do. Oh you are saying he will say I am
going to treat it as טמא tamei to prevent you from acting
that way. Okay, but maybe, but it is still speculative. We have
no basis of, there is nothing in בית שמאי Beit Shammai that
proves... No, but he is claiming it is בית שמאי’s Beit Shammai
position. And what the argument is if you wanted to say it
on your own, say it on your own, but there is nothing
that shows that בית שמאי’s Beit Shammai logic of 11 and 12
would lead to saying such a thing. Okay, that is the counterpoint.
So now the גמרא Gemara says ותנן, ve'otnan, now we are going
to try to prove again that according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai
if you have gone to the מקוה mikvah on day six, maybe
you should not act in certain ways for the rest of six,
maybe everything is in limbo, but it does not mean you are
treated as definitely טמא. tamei. How are we going to try to
show this? Let us take a look. Here is a משנה mishna
in זבים. Zavim. So we are back now with men. הרואה ראיה
אחת של זב, Haroeh reiyah achat shel zav, a man sees one
flow of a זיבה ziva flow, non-seminal, some other type of emission
from his penis, בית שמאי אומרים כשומר יום כנגד יום. Beit Shammai
omrim kishomer yom keneged yom. He is like a woman who saw
one day during her זיבה ziva period. Which means what? Which means
that anything she handles because why? If he bleeds a second time,
what is the הלכה halacha of a זב? zav? A זב zav
if he bleeds twice as opposed to a woman who is a
זבה zavah three times, a man it is two. If a man
sees a flow twice he becomes a זב zav and needs seven
clean days. How spaced do those two have to be as opposed
to a woman where the bleeding is only two separate days, two
consecutive but separate days, if a woman bleeds multiple times on the
same day it does not change her status. If a man has
a flow even twice on the same day he is a זב.
zav. So so you do not need it to be on consecutive
days. However, if he flows on on non-consecutive days, say day one
and day three he is not a זב. zav. Okay, so on
the one hand it it cannot be go beyond being consecutive, but
it does not have to be on the next day. It can
even be two flows on the same day.
A single flow
he has the status of a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. That is
only by the second flow he is treated as a זב zav
even on the same day but not on a non-consecutive day. But
three and a man it is
two.
A בעל קרי ba'al keri is טמא tamei day...
until he goes to the מקוה mikvah he is טהור tahor that
night. Right. So here...
wait a minute so. Yes. But we said before that a woman
who has sex after she goes to the מקוה mikvah on day
11,
the husband and wife are both טמא. tamei. Yes. What is the
source of that טומאה tumah for the man?
Well because the גמרא Gemara well we will see a מדרש midrash
quoted tomorrow, מדרש הלכה midrash halacha that the but anyway the תורה
Torah says that if a man sleeps with a woman who is
a נדה niddah then he becomes טמא tamei like she is. It
is a פסוק pasuk in the תורה. Torah. It says...
So he is טמא tamei because of what? Exposure to the...
No no if he just touched her he would be טמא tamei
as a derivative, like she is an אב av and he is
a ראשון. rishon. If he has sex with her then the תורה
Torah says that if a man has sex with a woman who
is a נדה niddah or a זבה zavah the גמרא Gemara assumes
it applies the same, then he has exactly her טומאה. tumah. He
has a seven-day טומאה. tumah.
So the act of sex
somehow... discharge from your penis does not make you טמא. tamei.
Well it makes you a בעל קרי ba'al keri but it does
not make you a seven-day טומאה tumah even in the
context of sex.
Yes. So so a husband and wife have sex at night and
he wants to if he is a כהן kohen basically, I mean
this is an interesting thing to think about how it impacted the
domestic life of כהנים. kohanim. But besides having to the women one
week out of the month having to basically avoid all תרומה, terumah,
you know, and so on, the every time during the rest of
the month that they had sex the man could not touch any
תרומה terumah until he has gone to the מקוה, mikvah, right? And
then you know and then he waits until nightfall. So any so
the day after having had sex the man could not touch any
תרומה. terumah. So the wife of כהנים kohanim the domestic life of
כהנים kohanim was really a big challenge.
What if he sleeps with a זב? zav? And she becomes a...
No no the idea of the transfer is only her status transferring
to him, not the reverse.
So if a woman... he is a זב zav he does not
transfer
his status to her the wife. Right. It probably goes back more
to this idea of the, well it could be a sense of
like...
you know well well you know it could be a general sense
of like the you know maybe the contaminant nature of the טומאה
tumah of נדה niddah and זבה zavah which we do not find
I would say in the תורה, Torah, we find it definitely you
know I mentioned this once before the whole taboos associated with it
whatever the רמב"ן Ramban ties it into the פסוק pasuk by by
רחל Rachel and her father I cannot get up or whatever the
avoidance of women
there. But in the actual Five Books of Moses, in the
הלכות, halachot, the מצוות mitzvot in the תורה, Torah, you don't see
that reflected, it's more,
but you could argue that maybe that's a part of it, I
don't know, or it could have to do more with generally
the
getting the blood out.
Yeah, but she's getting the זיבה ziva in her. She's getting the
זיבה ziva in her. And it might have to do again with
women
being... it might have to do also with I don't know, I
have to think about it.
Now this is very important because
I understand, I just don't know the answer. I mean the other
thing I'm thinking, but I'm not sure it's consistent, is does it
have to do with seeing men more as the subjects of action
and women more as the objects? But I'm not sure why that
should be true. Like, okay, so he was engaged with
a נדה. niddah.
And נדה niddah is now being absorbed by her? Just as it's
becoming...
I understand, I understand the question.
If you look at it all from the man's perspective, which the
תורה Torah does, then you could sort of say, he's handling, as
it were, if he handles טמא tamei things, he becomes טמא. tamei.
If he has effects with a woman who's טמא, tamei, he gets
contaminated, he becomes טמא. tamei. If you look at things like handling
other טמא tamei things, so it's him, it's all looked at him
as the subject. Whereas so I'm not so sure the flip, therefore,
if the focus is on him as the subject and him becoming
טמא tamei based on things he handles, I'm not so sure the
flip is obviously true. If she is טמא tamei and engages with
a woman, that she would become טמא. tamei.
And a woman makes another woman טמא? tamei?
By touch, yes. But the same way you could make food טמא
tamei by touch.
No, but if a woman has relations with another woman?
No, no, no. Sex is biblically, no, correct. What? Yeah. Yeah.
That's a whole other discussion that I am not
having.
Now sex, they can't, after they have regular sex, they can't touch
each other until he goes to the מקווה. mikvah. Right.
So but after he goes to the מקווה, mikvah, he's a טבול
יום, tevul yom,
he also can't touch her.
He still can't. Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so now
you're saying, I just want to basically implying that rabbinically the טומאת
נדה tumat niddah טומאה tumah is a greater taboo
than the זיבה... ziva... Not rabbinically, the תורה!
Torah! The תורה Torah is explicit! If a man has sex with
a נדה, niddah, the פסוק pasuk in the תורה, Torah, he gets
her טומאה.
tumah. And it doesn't talk about it by a זב, zav, right?
Correct. So I'm just saying it's not rabbinically, it's biblically. Okay.
That's this distinction she is in status of a זב. zav. Yes.
Without any contact. Yes. A man who is a זב zav can
have sex with his wife. Yes. And she can touch his זיבה
ziva
externally.
Right, right. If she touches the זיבה ziva externally, then she's a
ראשון. rishon. But she doesn't get his equal טומאה tumah if it's
only internal, it only goes into her body without external.
טומאת נדה tumat niddah is a greater טומאה tumah than... they're not
equivalent.
Correct, correct. I until now thought they were equivalent.
Well, the other difference is that נדה niddah is natural. נדה niddah
is natural, so every woman, even based on her natural biology, is
טמאה tmeiah for seven days. A man, the only natural thing is
קרי, keri, seminal emission. Right, I mean even that doesn't happen regularly,
but even when it happens, it's only a one-day טומאה. tumah. So
already there's that difference. Okay. Now, once a man is a זב,
zav, which is an unnatural status, his טומאה tumah is pretty identical
to that of a נדה niddah and זבה, zavah, but you're right,
with this difference. First of all, with the difference that he's not
prohibited in having sex with any woman. A נדה niddah and זבה
zavah is prohibited in having sex. He's not prohibited. A זב zav
is not prohibited in having sex. The other difference you're correct is
that if they have sex, then by the נדה, niddah, the טומאה
tumah status transfers to the man and by the זב, zav, his
status does not transfer to the woman.
זבה? zavah? Her status transfers to him as well. For seven days,
then he's seven days? According to the בעל המאור, Baal HaMaor, the
רמב״ם Rambam says, I mean I actually... the בעל המאור, Baal HaMaor,
the semen comes out... first of all, not זיבה ziva you mean
זב zav as a זב. zav. Yeah, so the בעל המאור, Baal
HaMaor, it's
the זב zav is considered to be first of all less viscous,
more fluidic, fluidic. It's not bloody, it's not bloody.
So then woman when she's a זבה, zavah, wouldn't be blood, she
wouldn't see blood?
No, a woman, it's about bleeding and what time of the month.
If she bleeds in a certain time of the month, she's a
נדה, niddah, another time of the month, the eleven days, she's a
זבה. zavah. A man, it's about what comes out of his body.
If semen comes out of his body, he's a בעל קרי. baal
keri. זב zav flow comes out, unnatural flow, which is basically defined
as something that is less viscous, more fluidic, it still has a
clear whitish color, and as the רמב״ם Rambam describes it also, he
says, contrasting it to בעל קרי, baal keri, he says there's no
pleasure in it leaving the body, and that so it's completely not
semen. Which is basically defined as something that is less viscous, more
fluidy, it still has a clear whitish color, and as the רמב"ם
Rambam describes it also, he says, contrasting it to בעל קרי, Ba'al
keri, he says there's no pleasure in it leaving the body and
that, you know, so it's completely not semen. So that is זיבה,
Ziva, and there's a משניות Mishnayos that discuss how to identify the
nature of the flow that makes him a זב. Zav. Okay, let's
move on. You don't want to not do the last, you know,
be so behind that we can't finish on the last day. So
the גמרא Gemara says
Friday, which is tomorrow.
Tomorrow. Yes, Friday is the... Did I tell you Friday? I did.
Yeah. Oh, oh, no,
my mistake. Friday is the first new day. Okay, sorry. Tomorrow's the
last day.
No, we don't. Moving on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
דתנן, Detnan, we saw in the משנה, Mishna, הרואה ראייה אחת של
זב, Ha'roeh reiyah achas shel zav, back to this, a man has
a flow that makes him a זב Zav now. What's his status?
If he bleeds again, if he sees another flow either today or
tomorrow, he becomes a זב, Zav, seven day טומאה, Tumah, etc. Okay,
what's his status in this period where he has yet to have
another flow? He's the status of a בעל קרי. Ba'al keri. Nevertheless,
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says, בית שמאי אומרים כשומרת יום כנגד יום,
Beis Shammai omerin ke'shomeres yom keneged yom, so he is like a
woman who bled one day, which means that even after he goes
to the מקוה, Mikvah, what's the status of a woman after she's
gone to the מקוה Mikvah if she bleeds on five and she
goes to the מקוה Mikvah on six? That everything is in abeyance
based on whether she'll bleed later that day. So he says this
man bled on one day, had a flow on one day, went
to the מקוה Mikvah the next, and he could have gone to
the מקוה Mikvah that day, whatever, went to the מקוה Mikvah the
next, until he goes the next day without having another flow, because
if he has another flow he'll be a זב, Zav, right? Anything
he touches will be held in abeyance. Now, that's not the real
הלכה. Halacha. The real הלכה Halacha is that even when the second
flow makes him a זב, Zav, but it doesn't connect to the
first. It doesn't retroactively undermine the טבילה. Tevila. Okay, so it will
make him a זב, Zav, but it won't change that middle period.
But בית שמאי Beis Shammai is saying like he said by the
woman of eleven and twelve, right?
Biblically speaking a new flow will change his status and make him
a זב, Zav, but won't undermine the טבילה, Tevila, but I'm going
to rabbinically say that it will. So I am going to say
those days in between will be that time in between after having
gone to the מקוה Mikvah will be held in abeyance. That's what
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says. ובית הלל אומרים כבעל קרי. U'Veis Hillel
omerin ke'ba'al keri. No, I'm sorry, it's like a man that went
to the מקוה Mikvah and is waiting for nightfall to be טהור,
Tahor, and he's a בעל קרי Ba'al keri and no time is
in held in abeyance based on if he flows later. If he
flows later he'll be a זב, Zav, but it won't retroactively affect
what's going on right now. Okay, so now let's take a look
at what at some more details about that. דתניא, Detanya, we saw
in the ברייתא, Baraisa,
המסיט את הראייה, Hamaseet es hareiyah, this man had this flow, okay,
this one day flow or one time flow, it has the status
of being even though it's not semen, when it's only once it
has the status of being like a seminal emission, like בעל קרי.
Ba'al keri. Now, here's a difference, by the way, about the actual
flow itself, the liquid itself, the fluid, which is if you touch
semen you're טמא. Tamei. If however you carry or move semen you
are not. However, by the זב Zav flow, this unnatural flow, even
if you move it or carry it you are also טמא. Tamei.
Okay, so now that is true when he's a זב Zav by
the second day. What's the status of the first flow? Okay, by
the second time, what's the status of the first flow? Is this
all clear? The first time his status, even though he has a
non-seminal emission, it's a זב Zav flow, his status is as a
בעל קרי. Ba'al keri. בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, if second time he's
a זב, Zav, בית שמאי Beis Shammai is treating it as the
beginning of the זב Zav process, so even if you've gone to
the מקוה Mikvah your status is in abeyance. Now let's talk about
the nature of the fluid itself. Are you going to treat it
like קרי Keri or are you going to treat it like זב?
Zav?
What's the time limit for the two times?
They have to be within they can't be separated by a full
day, okay, by a day. So they have to be at least
in juxtaposed days. Okay, so בית שמאי אומרים תולים, Beis Shammai omerin
tolim, the status of that that fluid is in abeyance. If he
if he has another flow within that day or the next day,
then it's continuous זב Zav process and that fluid will be treated
as a זב Zav fluid, and and if not, then it'll just
be like a seminal emission. ובית הלל מטהרים. U'Veis Hillel metaherim. And
בית הלל Beis Hillel says it's טהור. Tahor. So is this pretty
clear what the difference of the debate is? Yes? First time his
status is a זב, Zav, but he as a בעל קרי, Ba'al
keri, but he had a זב Zav flow. If he has a
new זב Zav flow he becomes a זב. Zav. So will the
second thing change the nature of what he was before? Make say,
oh now that he has the second one and he's a זב
Zav now, in a way the זב Zav period started back then.
So even having gone to the מקוה Mikvah didn't count, and the
flow is really זב Zav flow and so on. That's what בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says no, there
his status was בעל קרי, Ba'al keri, if he has another flow
from that point on he's a זב, Zav, but until then it's
all like a בעל קרי. Ba'al keri. That's the debate. ובית הלל
מטהרים משכבות ומושבות שבין ראייה ראשונה לראייה שנייה. U'Veis Hillel metaherim mishkavos
u'moshavos she'bein reiyah rishona l'reiyah shniyah. ובית הלל מטהרים, U'Veis Hillel metaherim,
excuse
me, משכבות ומושבות Mishkavos u'moshavos שבין ראייה... she'bein reiyah...
Between the first and second flow. Now let's say in exactly this
that he sat on various seats after the between the first and
second flow, so what's the הלכה *halacha*? So בית שמאי Beis Shammai
*Beit Shammai* מטמאים *metam'im* and בית הלל *Beit Hillel* מטהרים *metaherim*, same
point. בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* says it's going to be held in
abeyance. If you have another flow, it's all part of, it's like
all one big process and even that intermittent middle period is טמא
tamei *tamei*. And בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says no, it's a new
thing and what happened between the two, having if you've gone to
the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* after the first one, is not a problem.
I don't know, just spelling it out.
Okay, spelling out what the ספר *sefer* says. So anyway, what do
you see? You see that what בית הלל *Beit Hillel*, בית שמאי
*Beit Shammai* says? בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* says a man who saw
a first flow as a זב *zav*, not as a בעל קרי
*ba'al keri*, went to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah*. He says the next
period is like the period of שומרת יום כנגד יום *shomeret yom
k'neged yom*, of a woman who has blood on day five, went
to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* on day six. What does that mean?
It means what happens in that period is going to be determined
based on if you have a flow later that day. If you
bleed later that day, it's going to be held in abeyance. So
what do you see? You see that according to בית שמאי *Beit
Shammai*, a woman who goes to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* on day
six based on day five, goes on day six, is not straight
טמא tamei? *tamei*. He said it's the case of the man זב
*zav* is like the case of the woman, and the status is
held in abeyance based on is there going to be a flow
later that day. So your argument that בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* would
say you're straight טמא tamei? *tamei* that whole day even having gone
to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* is not true.
That's just a חומרא *chumra* by the woman, by the way.
What? That's biblical by the woman.
What's biblical? Held in abeyance. Yeah, but the point is
Rav Huna tried to argue that he would make her טמא tamei
*tamei* the whole day.
No, he would say just like בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* is adding
a stringency here, he would add a stringency.
Not adding a stringency. Oh, well, okay, let's you mean if you
think that בית שמאי's *Beit Shammai's* position here is not עיקר הדין
*ikkar hadin*, it's just a stringency. Okay, so let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but the point is it doesn't
matter whether you could argue a difference. בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* said
explicitly that her status on, that this man's status as a בעל
קרי *ba'al keri* was the same as a שומרת יום *shomeret yom*.
So and the status of this man, not of the בעל קרי
*ba'al keri*, as a זב *zav* is held in abeyance. And he,
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*, said it's like a שומרת יום *shomeret yom*.
So you see according to בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*, the five and
six scenario is held in abeyance, it's not straight טמא tamei. *tamei*.
But what's the actual implications, whether if she touches the תרומה trumah
*terumah* on that day, right?
After having gone to the מקוה *mikvah*?
Yeah, and then she bleeds, then it is held
in abeyance, then it is retroactively טמא tamei *tamei*.
What's the difference between that and Rav Huna saying no, don't touch
it?
The difference is, no, Rav Huna didn't just say don't touch it,
Rav Huna said even if you don't bleed later that day, the
things you touched are טמא *tamei*. We're going to treat you as
טמא *tamei* the whole day regardless of if you bleed later that
day.
Right, but if she bleeds
later there's no difference.
It's retroactively טמא *tamei*. Right. So why would she touch it in
the first place?
Okay, fine, I don't know why, if she did! Right, if she
did, that's the question.
Touch all these scenarios only with the hands?
No, any part of the body.
If she brushed up against
something.
But I mean, they're
both saying don't touch it. Right. The question is if she did,
what's the status, and if she didn't bleed. Okay, anyway that's a
proof. על מה *Alma* you see שומרת יום כנגד יום *shomeret yom
k'neged yom* לבית שמאי *l'Beit Shammai* טהור *tahor* that he says this
status I'm giving this man who had one flow as a זב
*zav* is like a שומרת יום *shomeret yom*. What's the status he's
giving the man? That it's held in abeyance. What's going to be
based on if he's going to have another flow. And he says
it's like a שומרת יום *shomeret yom*, so you see it is
held in abeyance, he doesn't treat her straight as טמא *tamei* on
day six. Says the גמרא *Gemara*, לא תימא *Lo teima* שומרת יום
כנגד יום *shomeret yom k'neged yom*, אלא אימא *ela eima* כבועל שומרת
יום כנגד יום *k'boel shomeret yom k'neged yom*. Here we go back
to the having sex stuff. So it says, no, בית שמאי *Beit
Shammai* change the text. He didn't say that this man's זב *zav*
status was similar to the woman who's a שומרת יום *shomeret yom*,
the five-six case. There we would rabbinically treat the woman as טמא
*tamei* the whole day even if she didn't bleed. But how about
if a man had sex with that woman after she went to
the מקוה *mikvah* on the morning of day six? Sex, sex, sex.
All right, you know they say,
all right, I've got to tell
you
this joke.
What comes between fear and sex? And the answer is פינף *fynf*.
Okay, what? פינף *fynf*. That is Yiddish, fear, פינף *fynf*, sex. Okay,
anyway, so anyway so the proof says like this.
So anyway in the case of in the case he had sex
with her after having she went to the מקוה *mikvah* on day
six, so in that case,
what was I saying? So in that case his status, although בית
שמאי *Beit Shammai* would say I'll treat her as טמא *tamei* the
whole day even though she's gone to the מקוה *mikvah*, him who
is one degree removed, he had sex with her, him I'm going
to say I'm not going to treat him as טמא *tamei* straight,
I'll say like the basic law that it's held in abeyance. So
when he said the man as a זב *zav* is like a
שומרת יום *shomeret yom*, he didn't literally mean a שומרת יום *shomeret
yom* according to Rav Huna. She would be טמא *tamei* the whole
day six even if she went to the מקוה *mikvah*. But if
a man had sex with her after she went to the מקוה
*mikvah*, his status would be held in abeyance
and so bringing a קרבן *korban* possibly.
It's all rabbinic. So now... The גמרא says: מאי שנא
אי דלא מטמא משכב ומושב ומאי שנא אי דמטמיא ליה, mai shna
ee d'lo metamei mishkav u'moshav u'maishna ee d'metamei lei, so why are
we making a difference between him and her? This is not the
biblical question רבקה, Rifka, this is at the rabbinic level. After she
went to the מקוה on day six, why are we saying that
she... why are we saying that she is טמא and even after
she went to the מקוה and if he had sex with her
he is not? So it says: איהו דלא שכיחי ביה דמים לא
גזרו ביה רבנן איהי דשכיחי בה דמים גזרו בה רבנן. eehu d'lo
sh'chichi bei damim lo gozru bei rabanan eehi d'sh'chichi bah damim gozru
bah rabanan. He doesn't regularly have blood so they didn't make a...
she regularly does bleed so they made an... Of course, now that
he's had sex with her, his status is dependent on her status,
so it doesn't really make, you know, so much sense, but... but
the basic point is that maybe... well, let's take a look because
then the גמרא goes on and maybe clarifies it a little bit.
ומאי שנא בועל דלא מטמא ליה משכב
ומושב, u'maishna boel d'lo metamei lei mishkav u'moshav, ומאי שנא בועל דלא
מטמא ליה, u'maishna boel d'lo metamei lei,
ומאי שנא בועל דלא מטמא ליה, u'maishna boel d'lo metamei lei, right,
and why are you saying that the guy that had sex with
her is not טמא? Right. ומאי שנא בועל דלא מטמא ליה, u'maishna
boel d'lo metamei lei, right, why are you saying that the guy
that had sex with her is not טמא? So it says: משכב
ומושב דשכיח, mishkav u'moshav d'sh'chiach, things she sits on is very common.
So she went to the מקוה on day six. She's now going
to handle things, sit on things, whatever. All that natural stuff she
sits on and handles, right, you can tell her not to touch
תרומה trumah but you can't tell her not to sit on something.
So that's all going to happen. So that we could say מטמא
ליה, metamei lei, that we'll say will apply, everything she touches and
handles is טמא because that's going to happen regardless. She has to
touch things, she has to sit on things. בועל דלא שכיח, boel
d'lo sh'chiach, but a... excuse me, but a... having sex, hopefully you're
not going to have sex on that day because same way you're
hopefully not going to touch תרומה on that day because it's... you
might turn out to be forbidden sex. So that's a very unusual
case. Since it's a very unusual case, לא מטמא, lo metamei, we're
not going to make him טמא. So בית שמאי is going to
say she will... this is רב הונא's Rav Huna argument... she will
treat as טמא the whole day even if she went to the
מקוה on six because we're afraid she'll bleed later. If he has
sex with her, no. Why? Number one, he's one degree removed. These
scenarios don't happen so much to him. He doesn't get these cases
of bleeding and so on. And the final point is that hopefully
this scenario itself of having had sex after having gone to the
מקוה is not a scenario that will happen too likely so therefore
we don't apply it to him. Okay, I guess we will end
here. All right.